<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ Hibernate, Relational Persistence for Idiomatic Java
  ~
  ~ JBoss, Home of Professional Open Source
  ~ Copyright 2011 Red Hat Inc. and/or its affiliates and other contributors
  ~ as indicated by the @authors tag. All rights reserved.
  ~ See the copyright.txt in the distribution for a
  ~ full listing of individual contributors.
  ~
  ~ This copyrighted material is made available to anyone wishing to use,
  ~ modify, copy, or redistribute it subject to the terms and conditions
  ~ of the GNU Lesser General Public License, v. 2.1.
  ~ This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT A
  ~ WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A
  ~ PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU Lesser General Public License for more details.
  ~ You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public License,
  ~ v.2.1 along with this distribution; if not, write to the Free Software
  ~ Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston,
  ~ MA  02110-1301, USA.
  -->
<!--
    @author Emmanuel Bernard <emmanuel@hibernate.org>
-->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "../ogm.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="ogm-architecture">
  <title>Architecture</title>

  <note>
    <para>We have defined an abstraction layer represented by
    <classname>DatastoreProvider</classname> and
    <classname>GridDialect</classname>. It has successfully abstracted various
    key/value stores and we are working on testing it on other NoSQL
    families.</para>
  </note>

  <para>In this chapter we will will explore:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>the general architecture</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>how the data is persisted in the data grid</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>how we support JP-QL queries</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>Let's start with the general architecture.</para>

  <section>
    <title>General architecture</title>

    <para>Hibernate OGM is really made possible by the reuse of a few key
    components:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Hibernate ORM for JPA support</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Hibernate Search for indexing purposes</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>the NoSQL drivers to interact with the underlying
        datastore</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Infinispan's Lucene directory to store indexed in Infinispan
        itself</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Hibernate OGM itself</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/architecture-components.png"
                   format="PNG" role="html"/>
      </imageobject>

      <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata align="center" depth=""
                   fileref="images/architecture-components.png" format="PNG"
                   role="fo" scalefit="1" width="12cm"/>
      </imageobject>

      <caption><para>General architecture</para></caption>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>Hibernate OGM reuses as much as possible from the Hibernate ORM
    infrastructure. There is no need to rewrite an entirely new JPA engine.
    The <classname>Persister</classname>s and the
    <classname>Loader</classname>s (two interfaces used by Hibernate ORM) have
    been rewritten to persist data using concepts like
    <classname>GridDialect</classname> and
    <classname>DatastoreProvider</classname>s instead of JDBC. These
    implementations are the core of Hibernate OGM. We will see in <xref
    linkend="ogm-architecture-datapersisted"/> how the data is structured.
    Other than that, all the Create/Read/Update/Delete (CRUD) operations are
    implemented by Hibernate ORM.</para>

    <para>AS of today, we have implemented three datastore providers:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>a Map based datastore provider (for testing essentially)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>an Infinispan based datastore provider to persist your entities
        in Infinispan</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>a EHCache based datastore provider to persist your entities in
        EHCache</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>To implement JP-QL queries, Hibernate OGM converts the JP-QL string
    into an Hibernate Search query. This query is then executed against the
    Lucene indexes stored in Infinispan and return the list of matching
    entities. Hibernate Search also listens to entity changes thanks to
    Hibernate ORM events and update the Lucene indexes accordingly.</para>

    <note>
      <para>Complex JP-QL queries esp with collection joins will require
      capabilities beyond Hibernate Search's current approach. We have several
      ideas in mind to address this problem.</para>

      <para>We also plan to bind JP-QL queries to the underlying capability of
      the datastore</para>
    </note>

    <para>Hibernate OGM best works in a JTA environment. The easiest solution
    is to deploy it on a Java EE container. Alternatively, you can use a
    standalone JTA <classname>TransactionManager</classname>. We do explain
    how to in <xref
    linkend="ogm-configuration-environments-standalonejta"/>.</para>

    <para>Let's now see how and in which structure data is persisted in the
    NoSQL data store.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="ogm-architecture-datapersisted">
    <title>How is data persisted</title>

    <para>Hibernate OGM tries to reuse as much as possible the relational
    model concepts (at least when they are practical and make sense in OGM's
    case). For very good reasons, the relational model brought peace in the
    database landscape over 30 years ago. In particular, Hibernate OGM
    inherits the following philosophy traits:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>abstraction between the application object model and the
        persistent data model</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>persist data as basic types</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>keep the notion of primary key to address an entity</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>keep the notion of foreign key to link two entities (not
        enforced)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>If the application data model is too tightly coupled with your
    persistent data model a few issues arise including:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>any change in the application object hierarchy / composition
        must be reflected in the persistent data</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>any change in the application object model will require a
        migration at the data level</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>any access to the data by another application ties both
        applications losing flexibility</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>any access to the data from another platform become somewhat
        more challenging</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>serializing entities leads to many additional problems (see note
        below)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <note>
      <title>Why aren't entities serialized in the key/value entry</title>

      <para>There are a couple of reasons why serializing the entity directly
      in the datastore can lead to problems:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>When entities are pointing to other entities are you storing
          the whole graph?</para>

          <para>Hint this can be quite big!</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If so, how do you guarantee object identity or even
          consistency amongst duplicated objects?</para>

          <para>It might make sense to store the same object graph from
          different root objects.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>What happens in case of class schema change?</para>

          <para>If you add or remove a property or include a superclass, you
          must migrate all entities in your datastore to avoid deserialization
          issues.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </note>

    <para>Entities are stored as tuples of values by Hibernate OGM. More
    specifically, each entity is represented by a
    <classname>Map&lt;String,Object&gt;</classname> conceptually where the key
    represents the column name (often the property name but not always) and
    the value represents the column value as a basic type. We favor basic
    types over complex ones to increase portability (across platforms and
    across type / class schema evolution over time). For example a URL object
    is store as its String representation.</para>

    <para>The key where a given entity instance is stored is composed
    of:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>the table name</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>the primary key column name(s)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>the primary key column value(s)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>This gives us several interesting properties. An entity is
    addressable by a single lookup. All entity types can live in the same key
    name space as they are entirely isolated.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/data-entity.png"
                   format="PNG" role="html"/>
      </imageobject>

      <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata align="center" depth="" fileref="images/data-entity.png"
                   format="PNG" role="fo" scalefit="1" width="12cm"/>
      </imageobject>

      <caption><para>Storing entities</para></caption>
    </mediaobject>

    <para/>

    <para>Associations are also stored as tuple as well or more specifically
    as a set of tuples. Hibernate OGM stores the information necessary to
    navigate from an entity to its associations. This is a departure from the
    pure relational model but it ensures that association data is reachable
    via key lookups based on the information contained in the entity tuple we
    want to navigate from. Note that this leads to some level of duplication
    as information has to be stored for both sides of the association.</para>

    <para>The key in which association data are stored is composed of:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>the table name</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>the column name(s) representing the foreign key to the entity we
        come from</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>the column value(s) representing the foreign key to the entity
        we come from</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Using this approach, we favor fast read and (slightly) slower
    writes.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/data-association.png"
                   format="PNG" role="html"/>
      </imageobject>

      <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata align="center" depth=""
                   fileref="images/data-association.png" format="PNG"
                   role="fo" scalefit="1" width="12cm"/>
      </imageobject>

      <caption><para>Storing associations</para></caption>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>Note that this approach has benefits and drawbacks:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>it ensures that all CRUD operations are doable via key
        lookups</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>it favors reads over writes (for associations)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>but it duplicates data</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <note>
      <para>We might offer alternative association data persistence options in
      the future based on feedback.</para>
    </note>

    <para>Some identifiers require to store a seed in the datastore (think
    about sequences for examples). The seed is stored in the value whose key
    is composed of:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>the table name</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>the column name representing the segment</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>the column value representing the segment</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Many NoSQL stores have no notion of schema. Likewise, the tuple
    stored by Hibernate OGM is not tied to a particular schema: the tuple is
    represented by a <classname>Map</classname>, not a typed
    <classname>Map</classname> specific to a given entity type. Nevertheless,
    JPA does describe a schema thanks to:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>the class schema</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>the JPA physical annotations like <classname>@Table</classname>
        and <classname>@Column</classname>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>While tied to the application, it offers some robustness and
    explicit understanding when the schema is changed as the schema is right
    in front of the developers' eyes. This is an intermediary model between
    the strictly typed relational model and the totally schema-less approach
    pushed by some NoSQL families.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>How is data queried</title>

    <para>TODO</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
